Edward Vaisman

☑ vaismanedward@gmail.com | ② eddyv | 🖨 edwardvaisman.ca | 🛅 edwardvaisman | 📞 (+1) 647-219-6236

Professional Summary_

Software engineer with 8+ years of expertise specializing in distributed systems and event-driven architectures. Proven track record in designing and implementing enterprise-scale Kafka ecosystems, cloud-native solutions, and real-time data pipelines across various cloud providers. Known for architecting sophisticated systems - from protocol-level engineering to Al-powered applications - while championing technical excellence and automating workflows.

Professional Experience



Confluent

Staff Partner Innovation Engineer

Toronto, ON

Oct 2022 - Current

- Designed & built a Kafka proxy to interpret Kafka's wire protocol, bridging clients and brokers to unlock advanced Confluent Cloud use
 cases via pluggable modules (Authentication Transformers, Interceptors).
- · Developed a DynamoDB Source Connector for a client, later promoted to a fully managed source connector.
- · Enhanced consumption tracking methodologies, driving insights into confluent cloud usage and billing.
- Delivered an end-to-end Generative AI and Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) application, integrating Confluent, Apache Flink, AI
 Model Inference, MongoDB Atlas, and a suite of AWS services (including Lambda, API Gateway, Secrets Manager, and S3), showcased at
 AWS re:Invent and webinars as a go-to-market initiative, strengthening strategic partnerships through co-marketing and technical
 collaboration.
- · Engineering cutting-edge Model Context Protocol (MCP) architectures to enhance LLM capabilities and RAG system integration.

Kafka Flink KStream Model Context Protocol Terraform Java Vert.x GenAl AWS GCP Azure

%//

Wavelo (Tucows)

Senior Staff Engineer (Kafka)

Toronto, ON

Nov 2020 - Oct 2022

- · Architected multi-datacenter Kafka infrastructure with Schema Registry, MirrorMaker2, and Connect.
- · Developed automation for provisioning, maintaining, and monitoring Kafka environments using the HashiCorp stack.
- Implemented observability solutions, creating real-time monitoring dashboards to track Kafka cluster connectivity, security, and performance. (DataDog, ElasticSearch, Prometheus, Grafana)
- Built self-serve GitOps tools to increase speed and productivity of developers using the kafka platform. (Topic Management, ACL Management, Kafka Connect Cluster Deployment, KSQL Deployment, Self-Hosted GitHub Runners, etc...)
- Increased our PaaS offerings by building an in-house CLI to interact with our private cloud infrastructure to deal with secret management, volume management, application deployment. (Typer CLI, Nomad APIs, Vault APIs)
- · Optimized Kafka performance by identifying bottlenecks and implementing throughput enhancements.
- · Ensured system reliability through rigorous disaster recovery testing and routine backup and restoration exercises.
- Educated staff on Kafka architecture, Schema Registry, and event-driven design principles, fostering company-wide adoption of best practices.

Kafka Terraform Nomad Vault SaltStack Docker GitHub Actions Prometheus Grafana DataDog ElasticSearch



Bank Of Montreal (BMO)
Senior Application Developer

Toronto, ON

Sept 2018 - Oct 2020

- Played a key role in advancing the bank's Customer Intelligence Platform by delivering a near real-time solution to provide the business with a unified view of customer interactions and enhance customer experience.
- Designed and implemented a secure, field-level encrypted real-time data pipeline enabling seamless data transfer between on-premises and cloud-based Kafka clusters (AWS).
- · Developed and optimized real-time streaming data pipelines to facilitate reliable data exchange across systems and applications.

Kafka Kafka Streams Java Spring Boot AWS



Toronto, ON

May 2016 - Sept 2018

- $\bullet \ \, \text{Designed and developed scalable, responsive, and robust web pages optimized for high performance \& conversion rates.}$
- · Managed web pages, email hosting, and web hosting services to ensure seamless client operations and user satisfaction.
- · Delivered detailed software solutions encompassing animations, scripting, and CMS development.

HTML CSS JavaScript PHP WordPress JQuery Google Apps Scripts SEO

Skills

Programming Java, Python, Bash, C#, XNA Game Studio

Web HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, Tailwindcss, Astro, WordPress, React

Big Data Confluent, Kafka, Flink, DataHub

Cloud AWS, GCP, Azure, OpenStack, DigitalOcean

DevOps GitHub, GitHub Actions, SaltStack, Terraform, Nomad, Vault, Docker, GitLab, Ansible, Maven

Education

York University

Toronto, ON

Sept 2013 - April 2018

B.Sc, Spec. Hons. Computer Science (Software Development)

Edward Vaisman Curriculum vitae